Tarun Kumar Pothineni

+1 (607) 296-8981 | tarunkumarpothineni@gmail.com | linkedin.com/in/tarun-kumar-pothineni/| https://tarunpothineni.dev/

Professional Summary

Full-stack developer with 2.5 years of experience in microservices architecture, database management, and Agile methodologies. Pursuing an MS in Computer Science at the State University of New York, Binghamton, with a proven ability to optimize system performance, enhance AI models, and drive business impact.

EDUCATION

Master of Science in Computer Science

State University of New York, Binghamton GPA: 3.940/4

Bachelors of Technology in Electronics and Communication Engineering

The LNM Institute of Information Technology GPA: 3.24/4

Aug 2023 - Present

Binghamton, NY

Aug 2017 - Jun 2021

Jaipur, India

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Language & Testing:: Java, Python, C, C++, Python, SQL, R, JavaScript, JUnit, Mockito Python Libraries: Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, scikit-learn, PyTorch, Tensor-Flow, Keras Frameworks: Spring Boot, Hibernate, gRPC, Selenium, Lambda, Maven Cloud: AWS (S3, SQS, Glue, Lambda, Sagemaker, EMR, Kinesis) Data: Apache (Spark, Hadoop, Kafka, Airflow) Database: SQL Server, MySQL, Postgres, Mongo DB, Volt DB, SingleStore, Oracle DB Tools and Technologies: Docker, Kubernetes, Jenkins, Rest APIs, Git, Jira, Agile, SDLC, WaterFall, Jupyter, Eclipse, Visual Studio, Postman, Terraform, Splunk, Linux, Unix, Tomcat, Bitbucket, ElasticSearch, Kibana, Grafana, DBeaver, GitLab, Ansible

EXPERIENCE

Senior Engineer, Comviva Technologies Limited, Bengaluru

Dec 2022 – Jul 2023

- Spearheaded a Proof of Concept to upgrade the database, slashing costs by 66% and boosting efficiency by 15% compared to VOLTDB, while migrating 23 microservices seamlessly to Singlestore.
- Designed and launched a Purchase History-based Offer Holdout feature, driving a 17% increase in client revenue by optimizing offer distribution to recent customers.
- Developed a Lambda architecture for real-time offer delivery, accelerating traffic by 60% and amplifying revenue by 40%, while creating a KTable and KStreams accumulator to expedite transaction processing and offer allocation.

Engineer, Comviva Technologies Limited, Bengaluru

Jul 2021 – Nov 2022

- Revamped an existing microservice by integrating caching, streamlining database queries, and optimizing code, reducing customer offer delivery time by 71.4%.
- Integrated all microservices with Consul, removing reliance on external configuration files and enhancing multi-deployment compatibility and seamless inter-service communication.
- Deployed the EFK stack for centralized logging, improving log collection, aggregation, and analysis by 40%.
- Configured and launched Grafana for real-time monitoring and visualization, increasing system observability by 30%.
- Optimized PostgreSQL queries in a microservice, boosting efficiency and reducing output response time by 600ms.

Engineer Trainee, Comviva Technologies Limited, Bengaluru

Jan 2021 – Jul 2021

- Refined code quality and reduced production defects by achieving 80% code coverage through test-driven development.
- $\bullet \ \ \mathbf{Resolved} \ \ \mathbf{over} \ \ \mathbf{300+} \ \ \mathbf{real-time} \ \ \mathbf{bugs} \ \ \mathbf{during} \ \ \mathbf{client-server} \ \ \mathbf{deployment}, \ \mathbf{enhancing} \ \ \mathbf{system} \ \ \mathbf{stability} \ \ \mathbf{and} \ \ \mathbf{performance}.$

Projects

Enhanced YOLO Framework

Oct 2024 - Dec 2024

- Optimized the YOLOv7 model, improving mean Average Precision (mAP) by 3.1% and reducing inference time by 5.4%, enhancing detection speed and accuracy on the Pascal VOC 2012 dataset.
- Increased model precision by 2.4% and recall by 1.8% through hyperparameter tuning and efficient data preprocessing.
- Reduced GPU memory usage by 4.5% and enhanced overall model efficiency, accelerating training cycles on Google Colab with a T4 GPU.

HandWritten Digits Recognition

Feb 2024 – Apr 2024

- Developed an Android app using Java and TensorFlow Lite to predict handwritten digits with a custom CNN model, achieving 98.97% accuracy and reducing latency to 2ms.
- Evaluated inbuilt models such as ResNet50, and MobileNetV3, achieving accuracies of 98.55% and 96.64%, respectively.
- Implemented a robust machine learning solution with a 4-layer CNN, trained over 7 epochs using the Adam optimizer and dropout regularization, outperforming traditional models.